<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubuxsercontent.com/srophe/srophe-eXist-app/master/srophe-app/documentation/enrich-syriaca.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="SRPEnrichCSS.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">London, BL, Add. 14641</title>
        <sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor>
        <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
        <funder>The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
        <principal>David A. Michelson</principal>
        <editor role="general-editor" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
        <editor role="creator" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#wwright">William Wright</editor>
        <editor role="creator" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor>
        <editor role="creator" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#dgreeson">Daniel J. Greeson</editor>
        <editor role="creator" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#pgmiller">Peter G. Miller</editor>
        <editor role="creator" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#raydin">Robert Aydin</editor>
        <editor role="creator" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#jarnwine">Justin Arnwine</editor>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Created by</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#pgmiller">Peter G. Miller</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Based on the work of</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#wwright">William Wright</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Edited by</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#pgmiller">Peter G. Miller</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Syriac text entered by</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#raydin">Robert Aydin</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Greek and coptic text entry and proofreading by</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#rstitt">Ryan Stitt</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Project management by</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#ewalston">Elizabeth Walston</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>English text entry and proofreading by</resp>
          <name type="org" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#uasyriacaresearchgroup">Syriac Research Group, University of Alabama</name>
        </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
          <resp>Syriaca.org URIs for authors edited by</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#jarnwine">Justin Arnwine</name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Syriaca.org URIs for authors checked by</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#aahn">Alexys Ahn</name>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#jdalfonso">Joseph DAlfonso</name>
        </respStmt>
      <respStmt>
          <resp>Folio extent edited by</resp>
          <name type="person" ref="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#kurban">Kurt Urban</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="1.0"/>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <pubPlace/>
        <authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority>
        <idno type="URI">https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/405/tei</idno>
        <availability>
          <p/>
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License</p>
          </licence>
        </availability>
        <date calendar="Gregorian">2023-04-21-05:00</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc xml:id="manuscript-405" xml:lang="en">
          <msIdentifier>
            <country>United Kingdom</country>
            <settlement>London</settlement>
            <repository>British Library</repository>
            <collection>Oriental Manuscripts</collection>
            <idno type="URI">https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/405</idno>
            <altIdentifier>
              <idno type="BL-Shelfmark">Add. 14,641</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier>
              <idno type="BL-Shelfmark-display">London, BL, Add. 14,641</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier>
              <idno type="BL-Shelmark-simplified">BL Add MS 14641</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier>
              <collection>William Wright, Catalogue of the Syriac Manuscripts in the British Museum Acquired since the Year 1838</collection>
              <idno type="Wright-BL-Arabic">918</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
            <altIdentifier>
              <collection>William Wright, Catalogue of the Syriac Manuscripts in the British Museum Acquired since the Year 1838</collection>
              <idno type="Wright-BL-Roman">DCCCCXVIII</idno>
            </altIdentifier>
          </msIdentifier>
          <head>
            <note type="contents-note">This manuscript contains: A history and panegyric of Constantine the Greatand his three sons, Constantine, Constantius and Constans; A narrative concerning Eusebius, bishop of Rome, showing the persecution which he underwent at the hands of the emperor Julian; ܐܦܠܘܪܝܣ, ܐܠܦܠܘܠܪܝܣ. A history (or rather a historical romance) of the reign of the emperor Jovian, or, as he is here called, Jovinian, giving, in particular, a narrative of the war carried on byJulianand Jovian against the Persians.; A collection of Lives of Saints and Acts of Martyrs. In total, including sub-sections, this manuscript contains 11 items.</note>
            <listRelation type="Wright-BL-Taxonomy">
              <relation name="dcterms:type" ref="http://purl.org/dc/terms/type" active="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/405" passive="#history">
                <desc>History</desc>
              </relation>
            </listRelation>
          </head>
          <msContents>
            <summary/>
            <textLang mainLang="syr">Syriac</textLang>
            <msItem xml:id="a1" n="1" defective="true">
              <locus from="1a" to="1">1a-1</locus>
              <title type="supplied">A history and panegyric of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1655">Constantine the Great</persName> and his three sons, <persName>Constantine</persName>, <persName>Constantius</persName> and <persName>Constans</persName>
              </title>
              <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܢܨܚܢܐ ܕܥܠ ܗܝܡܢܘܬܗ ܕܩܘܣܛܢܛܝܢܘܣ ܘܕܬܠܬܐ ܒܢ̈ܘܗܝ ܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܐܡܠܟܘ ܒܬܪܗ<locus from="1a" to="1a"/>
              </rubric>
              <note>It is very imperfect.</note>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="a2" n="2" defective="true">
              <locus from="1b" to="31a">1b-31a</locus>
              
              <title type="supplied">A narrative concerning <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1723">Eusebius, bishop of Rome</persName>, showing the persecution which he underwent at the hands of the emperor <persName>Julian</persName>
              </title>
              <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܕܢܨ̈ܚܢܘܗܝ ܕܐܘܣܒܝܣ ܛܘܒܢܐ ܐܦܣܩܦܐ ܕܥܕܬܐ ܕܪܗܘܡܐ: ܒܝ̈ܘܡܝ ܝܘܠܝܢܘܣ ܛܪܘܢܐ ܘܥܘܪܠܐ.<locus from="1b" to="1b"/>
              </rubric>
              <note>Eusebius is said to have been at this time nearly 97 years old.</note>
              <quote xml:lang="syr">ܩܘܪܒܐ ܓܝܪ ܕܒܪ ܬܫ̈ܥܝܢ ܘܫܒܥ ܫ̈ܢܝܢ ܐܝܬܘܗܝ ܗܘܐ ܗܢܐ ܣܒܐ̣. ܟܕ ܩܐܡ ܒܐܓܘܢܐ ܕܡܘܕܝܢܘܬܐ.<locus from="2a" to="2a"/>
              </quote>
              <note>But he outlived Julian, dying A. Gr. 673.</note>
              <quote xml:lang="syr">ܩܘܝ ܕܝܢ ܛܘܒܢܐ ܐܘܣܒܝܣ ܒܚ̈ܝܐ̣. ܥܕܡܐ ܕܫܡ̣ܥ ܛܒ̣ܐ ܕܡܘܬܗ ܕܝܘܠܝܢܘܣ ܥܘܿܠܐ̇. ܘܕܚܕܝܬ ܘܪܘܙܬ ܪܘܚܗ̣ ܒܦܘܪܩܢܐ ܕܥ̣ܒܕ ܐܠܗܐ ܠܥܡܗ. ܘܐܬܒܝܐܬ ܣܝܒܘܬܗ ܒܦܘܬܚܗܝܢ ܕܥܕ̈ܬܐ̇. ܘܒܦܘܢܝܐ ܕܟܗ̈ܢܝܗܝܢ. ܘܒܟܢܘܫܝܐ ܕܝ̈ܠܕܝܗܝܢ. ܘܒܣܝܒܘܬܐ ܛܒܬܐ ܥܠ ܥܪܣܐ ܕܢܝܚܗ̣ ܗܘ̣ܐ ܥܘܢܕܢܗ ܡܢ ܥܠܡܐ̣. ܒܫܢܬ ܫܬܡܐܐ ܘܫܒܥܝܢ ܘܬܠܬ ܒܡܢܝܢܐ ܕܝܘ̈ܢܝܐ. ܕܐܝܬܝܗ̇ ܫܢܬ ܬܠܬܡܐܐ ܘܫܬܝܢ ܘܫܒܥ (sic) ܒܡܠܟܘܬܗ ܕܡܪܢ ܝܫܘܥ ܕܒܝܬ ܒ̈ܢܝ ܐܢܫܐ</quote>
              <finalRubric xml:lang="syr">ܫܠܡܬ ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܘܩܘܠܣܐ ܕܩܘܣܛܢܛܝܢܣ ܡ̇ܠܟܐ ܡܗܝܡܢܐ ܘܕܒ̈ܢܘܗܝ. ܘܬܫܥܝܬܗ ܕܛܘܒܢܐ ܐܘܣܒܝܣ. ܐܦܣܩܘܦܐ ܕܪܗܘܡܐ.<locus from="31a" to="31a"/>
              </finalRubric>
              <note>Eusebius was bishop of Rome A.D. 309-311. The actual bishop in the time of Julian was <persName>Liberius</persName>, A.D. 352-367.</note>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="a3" n="3" defective="true">
              <locus from="31a" to="131">31a-131</locus>
              <author>ܐܦܠܘܪܝܣ</author>
              <author>ܐܠܦܠܘܠܪܝܣ</author>
              <title type="supplied">A history (or rather a historical romance) of the reign of the emperor <persName>Jovian</persName>, or, as he is here called, Jovinian, giving, in particular, a narrative of the war carried on by <persName>Julian</persName> and Jovian against the Persians.</title>
              <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܝܘܒܢܝܢܘܣ<locus from="1a" to="131"/>
              </rubric>
              <incipit xml:lang="syr">ܟܬܒܐ ܕܟܬܒ ܥܒܕܐܝܠ ܪܝܫܕܝܪܐ. ܠܐܦܠܘܪܝܣ ܡܗܝܡܢܗ ܕܝܘܒܢܝܢܘܣ ܡ̇ܠܟܐ. ܕܠܗ ܐܬܗ̣ܝܡܢ ܣܘܥܪܢܐ ܕܦܘܣܩܢܐ ܕܗܘ̣ܐ ܒܝܬ ܡܠܟܘ̈ܬܐ. .ܘ:ܘ .ܘ:ܘ. ܘ:ܘ. ܐܢܫܐ ܒܪܝ ܦܪ̈ܘܫܐ̣ ܠܐ ܡܐܢܐ ܠܗܘܿܢ̇ ܐܡܬܝ ܕܐܢܫ ܡܢܗܘܢ ܢܫܐܠ ܡܘܗܒܬܐ. ܗ̇ܝ ܐܝܕܐ ܕܝܗܒܐ ܝܘܬܪܢܐ ܠܝܗ̈ܘܒܐ ܘܠܢܣܘ̈ܒܐ. ܐܟܙܢܐ ܓܝܪ ܕܡܒܘܥܐ: ܕܟܡܐ ܕܕܠܝܢ ܡܢܗ: ܪܕܝܗ ܡܥܬܪ ܥܬܪ: ܘܟܕ ܠܣ̈ܓܝܐܐ ܡܒܣܡ ܒܫܩܝܗ ܡܠܝܘܬܗ ܡܩܘܝܐ̣. ܒܗ̇ ܒܕܡܘܬܐ ܙܕܩ̇ ܠܝܗܘܒܐ̇. ܕܢܠܐܐ ܘܠܐ ܬܬܩܛܥ ܠܗ ܒܡܘܗܒܬܗ. ܕܟܕ ܠܐܢ̈ܫܐ ܣܢܝ̈ܩܐ ܡܥܬܪܐ̣. ܗ̣ܝ ܡܠܝܘܬܗ ܨܝܕ ܝܗܘܒܗ̇ ܫܪܟܐ. ܕܠܡܐ ܗܟܝܠ ܒܪܐ ܚܒܝܒܐ. ܕܚܪܬܐ ܛܒܬܐ ܕܓܒܪܐ ܪܘܚܢܐ̇. ܬܡܐܢ. ܠܟ ܒܦܝܣܗ̇ ܕܒܥܘܬܢ̇ ܕܝܘܬܪܢܐ ܡܢ ܟܕܘ ܐܝܬ ܒܗ̇ ܘܠܝܗ̈ܘܒܝܗ̇ ܘܠܢܣ̈ܘܒܝܗ̇. ܠܐ ܙܥܘܪ ܓܝܪ ܝܘܬܪܢܐ ܕܐܬܬܓܪܬ ܠܩܢܘܡܟ. ܕܡܬܦܢܝܢܘܬܗܝܢ ܕܢܦܫ̈ܬܐ ܣܓܝܐ̈ܬܐ̇. ܕܦܢܝ ܡܢ ܛܥܝܘܬܗܝܢ ܒܡܪܬܝܢܘܬܗ ܕܟܬܒܐ ܩܕܝܫܐ. ܕܫܕܪܬ ܠܢ ܪܒܘܬܟ. ܕܗܦܟܘ ܡܢ ܛܥܝܘܬܗܘܢ̣ ܘܐܣܬܡܟܘ ܥܠ ܬܝܒܘܬܐ. ܘܐܬܘ ܠܝܕܥܬܐ ܕܫܪܪܐ. ܝܕܥܬ ܓܝܪ ܚܒܝܒܝ̣. ܕܒܐܬܪܐ ܕܚ̈ܢܦܐ ܣܝܡܝܢ ܐܢܚܢܢ. ܘܒܕܡܘܬ ܦܪܚܬܐ ܕܒܠܩܛܐ ܡܬܓܢܒܐ ܠܨܝܕܐ̣. ܒܗ̇ ܒܕܡܘܬܐ ܐܦ ܚܢ̈ܦܐ ܒܠܩܛܗ ܕܝܘܠܦܢܐ̇. ܡܬܬܨܝܕܝܢ ܠܬܝܒܘܬܐ. ܣܒ ܗܟܝܠ ܒܪܝ ܛܥܢܗ̇ ܕܒܥܘܬܢ̇. ܘܗܒ ܠܢ ܬܫܥܝܬܗ ܘܣܟܗ ܕܩܪܒܐ ܕܗܘܐ ܒܝܬ ܡܠܟ̈ܘܬܐ̇. ܘܫܘܠܡܗ ܒܝܫ̣ܐ (fol. 31 b) ܘܫܩ̣ܠ ܚܝ̈ܘܗܝ ܕܛܪܘܢܐ. ܘܥܡ ܗܠܝܢ ܬܘܒ̣ ܐܦ ܩܘܠܣܗ ܘܪܘܒܘܬܗ ܕܝܘܒܝܢܝܢܘܣ ܡܪܟ. ܐܦ ܐܓܘܢܗܘܢ ܘܨܥܪܐ ܕܐܢܫܐ ܓܡܝܪ̈ܐ ܘܦܪ̈ܘܫܐ. ܕܐܩܪܒܘ ܥܡ ܡܣܝܒܐ ܘܪܕܘܦܐ ܘܡܪܚܐ̇. ܘܐܚܒܘ ܙܟܘܬܐ ܘܢܨܚܢܐ. ܘܟܕ ܩܒܠܘ ܐܢܝܢ ܐܦܠܘܠܪܝܣ ܠܟܬ̈ܝܒܬܗ ܕܥܒܕܐܝܠ ܪܝܫܕܝܪܐ̣. ܣܡ ܐܢܝܢ ܥܠ ܥ̈ܝܢܘܗܝ̣ ܘܢܫ̇ܩ ܐܢܝܢ. ܘܫܩ̣ܠ ܕܢܟܬܘܒ ܠܗ. ܒܙ̈ܒܢܘܗܝ ܕܝܘܠܝܢܣ ܚܢܦܐ. ܘܪܫܝܥܐ܆ ܗ̇ܘ ܕܩܒܠ ܗܘ̣ܐ ܡܠܟܘܬܐ ܡܢ ܕܒܝܬ ܩܘܣܛܢܛܝܢܘܣ̣. ܐܝܬ ܗ̣ܘܐ ܠܗ ܪܒ ܒܝܬܐ ܚܕ݂. ܕܫܡܗ ܗܘ̣ܐ ܝܘܒܝܢܝܢܘܣ. ܓܒܪܐ ܕܝܕܥܬܐ̣ ܘܕܣܘܟܠܐ. ܕܣܦ̣ܩ ܒܝܕܥܬܗ ܕܢܗܘܐ ܡܢ ܡܠܟ ܡ̈ܠܟܘܗܝ ܕܛܪܘܢܐ ܏ܘܫ<locus from="31a" to="31b"/>
              </incipit>
              <explicit xml:lang="syr">ܐܢܐ ܕܝܢ ܒܨܝܪܐ ܥܒܕܗ ܕܝܫܘܥ ܡܫܝܚܐ܆ ܐܦܠܘܪܝܣ ܡܗܝܡܢܐ ܕܝܘܒܢܝܢܘܣ ܡ̇ܠܟܐ̣. ܥܒܕ ܨܚ̈ܚܐ (fol. 131 a) ܗܠܝܢ ܠܡܝܬܪܐ ܘܪܚܡܐ ܕܐܠܗܐ.   ܡܪܝ ܥܒܕܐܝܠ ܪܝܫܕܝܪܐ ܕܣܢܕܪܘܢ ܡܚܘܙܐ. ܕܗܘ ܗܢܐ ܦܪܘܫܐ ܪܚܡ ܝܘܠܦܢܐ. ܒܝܕ ܡܫܡܫܢܗ ܒܥܐ ܡܢܢ. ܕܢܪܫܘܡ ܠܗ ܬܫܥܝܬܗ ܘܛܟܣܗ ܘܐܣܟܡܗ̇. ܕܩܪܒܐ ܗܢܐ ܕܗܘ̣ܐ ܒܝܘ̈ܡܬܢ.. ܟܕ ܬܒܥ ܠܢ ܕܢܫ̇ܪܐ ܒܬܫܥܝܬܢ ܡܢ ܥܘܢܕܢܗ ܚܫܝܫܐ ܕܩܘܣܛܢܛܝܢܘܣ ܡܗܝܡܢܐ. ܥܕܡܐ ܕܫܩܠܘ ܫܘܠܡܐ ܚܝܝ̈ܘܗܝ (sic) ܕܝܘܒܢܝܢܘܣ ܡܩܝܡܢܐ ܕܥ̈ܕܬܐ. ܥܒܕܢܢ ܕܝܢ ܨܒܝܢܐ ܠܒܥܘܬܗ ܕܟܗܢܐ ܙܗܝܐ. ܐܚܝܕ ܕܘܒܪ̈ܐ ܕܢܟܦܘܬܐ. ܘܒܙܕܩܗܝܢ ܘܒܣܕܪܗܝܢ ܒܬܪ ܒܬܪ. ܐܟܬܒܢ ܐܢܝܢ ܠܬܫܥ̈ܝܬܐ ܗܠܝܢ ܐܝܟܢܐ ܕܓܕܫ ܘܐܣܬܥܪ. ܟܕܠܐ ܐܘܣܦܢܢ ܐܘ ܒܨܪܢܢ ܡܢ ܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܩܕܡܝܢ ܐܣܬܥܪ. ܘܚܙܝ̈ܝܗܝܢ ܗܘܝܢܢ. ܦܫܢܢ ܕܝܢ ܡܢ ܕܠܡܬܢܐ ܬܫܥܝܬܗܝܢ̇ ܕܐܝܠܝܢ ܕܕܠܐ ܒܙܕܩܐ ܪܫܝܥܐܝܬ ܐܣܬܥܪ ܒܚܡܨ. ܗܢܘ ܕܝܢ ܒܡܥܒܕܢܘܬܗ ܕܝܘܠܝܢܘܣ ܛܪܘܢܐ. ܒܩܠܝܠ ܝܘܡ̈ܬܐ ܕܦܣܩ ܗܘ̣ܐ ܐܘܪܚܗ ܘܣ̣ܛܐ ܠܗ̇. ܗܢܘ ܕܝܢ ܡܛܠ ܕܫܡܥ ܥܠ ܫܒܝܚܘܬܗ ܕܢܘܣܗ̇ ܕܥܕܬܐ. ܕܒܢܐ ܒܗ ܩܘܣܛܢܛܝܢܘܣ ܪܚܡ ܠܡܫܝܚܐ. ܕܘܟܪܢܗ ܠܒܘܪܟܬܐ ܠܥܠܡܝܢ ܐܡܝܢ: ܠܛܢܢܗܘܢ ܕܚܢ̈ܦܐ. ܕܡܫܬܒܗܪܝܢ ܗܘܘ ܒܢܘܣܐ ܪܒܐ ܕܒ̣ܢܐ ܗܘ̣ܐ ܠܦܬܟܪ̈ܝܗܘܢ ܒܪܘܡܗ ܕܡܕܝܢܬܗܘܿܢ. ܠܗܢܐ ܦܘܪܣܐ ܙܩܬܗ ܛܢܢܐ ܠܝܘܠܝܢܘܣ ܫܢܝܐ̣. ܕܢܐܬܐ ܠܡܕܝܢܬܐ ܕܚ̈ܡܨܝܐ̣. ܐܝܟ ܕܢܘܫܒ ܐܝܕܗ ܒܢܘܣܗ̇ ܕܥܕܬܐ ܘܢܚܒܠܘܗܝ. ܘܟܕ ܥܠ ܘܚܙܝܗܝ ܬܗܪ ܒܗ ܒܫܘܦܪܐ ܕܒܢܝܢܗ. ܘܫܒ݁ܚ ܠܒ݁ܢܝܗ ܘܚܣ ܕܢܚܒܠܘܗܝ. ܘܐܬܪܥܝ ܕܢܥܒܕܘܗܝ ܒܝܬ ܣܓܕܬܐ ܠܦܬܟܪ̈ܘܗܝ. ܘܕܒ݁ܚ ܗܘ̣ܐ ܒܗ ܘܫܡܠܝ ܪ̈ܐܙܐ ܕܚܢܦܘܬܗ. ܘܐܚܕܗ ܘܛܒܥܗ ܒܥܙܩܬܗ. ܘܗܦܟ ܡܢ ܕܪܫ ܠܐܢܛܝܟܝܐ. ܘܐܚܕ ܐܘܪܚܐ ܕܡܐܙܠܬܗ. ܨ̇ܒܐ ܗܘܝܬ ܕܝܢ ܐܘ ܓܒܪܐ ܕܐܠܗܐ̣. ܕܐܦ ܥܘܗܕܢܐ ܕܬܝܒܘܬܗ ܕܐܣܛܝܢܐ ܡܠܟܬܐ. ܐܣܝܡ ܒܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܗܕܐ ܐܠܘ ܡܨܝܐ. ܕܝܘܬܪܢܐ ܐܝܬ ܒܗ̇ ܠܬܝ̈ܒܐ̇. ܐܠܐ ܡܛܠ ܕܨ̈ܒܘܬܐ ܕܡ̇ܠܟܐ ܡܒܠܗܝܢ ܡܢ ܟܕܘ. ܡܣܬܪܗܒܝܢܢ ܡܛܠ ܗܢܐ ܠܟ ܚܒܝܒ.  (fol. 131 b) ܩܠܝܠ ܡܢ ܣܓܝ ܟܬܒܬ ܕܬܬܗܓܐ ܥܕ ܗܘ̣ܐ ܠܢ ܙܒܢܐ ܫܦܝܪ. ܏ܘܫ..<locus from="130b" to="131b"/>
              </explicit>
              <note>The running title is simply <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܝܘܒܢܝܢܘܣ</foreign>, which occurs from the very commencement of the volume (see, for example, <locus>foll. 1 a, 8 b, 13 b, 18 b</locus>).</note>
              <note>
                <bibl>Land, Anecd. Syr., t. i., p. 21, note</bibl>, conjectures that we should read either <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܦܠܢܪܝܣ</foreign>, <persName>Apollinaris</persName>, or <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܦܠܘܢܝܣ</foreign>, <persName>Apollonius</persName>.</note>
              <note>
                <bibl>Land, Anecd. Syr., t. i., p. 22, note</bibl>, identifies this place with <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܢܕܪܝܗ</foreign> (sic) near <placeName>Maridin</placeName>, but this latter name is written by <bibl>Assemani, Bibl. Or., t. ii., p. 228</bibl>, <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܫܶܢܕܪܺܝܗ</foreign>, with shin.</note>
              <note>The name of the author is written <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܦܠܘܪܝܣ</foreign>, <locus>foll. 31 a, 130 b</locus>, and <foreign xml:lang="syr">ܐܠܦܠܘܠܪܝܣ</foreign>, <locus from="31b">fol. 31 b</locus>; and he calls himself a minister or official (<foreign xml:lang="syr">ܡܗܝܡܢܐ</foreign>) of <persName>Jovian</persName>. He composed the work at the request of <persName>'Abdil</persName>, abbat of the place called <placeName><foreign xml:lang="syr">ܣܢܕܪܘܢ ܡܚܘܙܐ</foreign></placeName>, with whose letter it commences.</note>
            </msItem>
            <msItem xml:id="a4" n="4" defective="true">
              <locus from="132a" to="171b"/>
              
              <title type="supplied">A collection of Lives of Saints and Acts of Martyrs</title>
              <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܥܠ ܣܒܪܐ ܫܪܝܪܐ ܘܠܐ ܡܒܗܬܢܐ: ܕܬܠܝܬܝܘܬܐ ܡܪܝܡܬܐ ܘܡܫܒܚܬܐ: ܟܬܒ ܐܢܐ ܬܫܥ̈ܝܬܐ ܡܘܬܪܬ ܢܦܫܐ: ܕܣܗ̈ܕܐ ܘܕܣܗ̈ܕܬܐ<locus from="132a" to="132a"/>
              </rubric>
              <msItem xml:id="b1" n="5">
                <locus from="132a" to="138">132a-138</locus>
                
                <title type="supplied">The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1497">Thecla</persName>, the disciple of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1984">S. Paul</persName>
                </title>
                <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܩܕܡܐܝܬ ܕܢܨܝܚܬܐ ܬܩܠܐ ܗ̇ܝ ܕܦܘܠܘܣ<locus from="132a" to="132a"/>
                </rubric>
                <note>See <bibl>Add. 12,174<ptr target="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/70"/>, no. 76</bibl>.</note>
              </msItem>
              <msItem xml:id="b2" n="6">
                <locus from="144a" to="145">144a-145</locus>
                
                <title type="supplied">Some account of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1826">S. John the Evangelist</persName>, followed by an account of the decease of S. John</title>
                <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܕܝܘܚܢܢ ܫܠܝܚܐ ܘܐܘܢܓܠܣܛܐ<locus from="144a" to="144a"/>
                </rubric>
                <quote xml:lang="syr">ܥܠ ܡܦܩܬܗ ܕܝܘܚܢܢ ܕܡܢ ܥܠܡܐ<locus from="145a" to="145a"/>
                </quote>
                <note>The text is an extract from the <ref>Ecclesiastical History of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/480">Eusebius</persName>, lib. iii., cap. 23</ref>. The second half is extracted from <ref>the Ecclesiastical History, lib. iii., cap. 31</ref>.</note>
              </msItem>
              <msItem xml:id="b3" n="7">
                <locus from="146a" to="149">146a-149</locus>
                
                <title type="supplied">The martyrdom of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/2020">Polycarp</persName>
                </title>
                <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܕܩܕܝܫܐ ܦܘܠܝܩܪܦܘܣ: ܕܐܣܗܕ ܒܫ̈ܢܝ ܐܘܪܘܣ ܥܡ ܐܚܪ̈ܢܐ: ܒܙܡܝܪܢܐ ܡܕܝܢܬܐ ܕܐܦܣܘܣ<locus from="146a" to="146a"/>
                </rubric>
                <note>This is also an extract from the <ref>Ecclesiastical History of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/480">Eusebius</persName>, lib. iv., comprising the last sentence of cap. 14 and the whole of cap. 15</ref>.</note>
              </msItem>
              <msItem xml:id="b4" n="8">
                <locus from="150a" to="156">150a-156</locus>
                
                <title type="supplied">The story of the Seven Youths of Ephesus, or the Seven Sleepers</title>
                <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܕܫ̈ܒܥܐ ܛ̈ܠܝܐ ܘܣܗ̈ܕܐ: ܕܐܬܢܚܡܘ ܒܡܥܪܬܐ ܕܐܝܟܠܣ ܛܘܪܐ ܕܐܦܣܘܣ ܐܬܪܐ<locus from="150a" to="150a"/>
                </rubric>
                <incipit xml:lang="syr">ܟܕ ܫܠܡ ܠܒܢܝܢܐ ܕܪܗܘܡܐ ܐܠܦ ܫ̈ܢܝܢ. ܘܐܓܘܢܐ ܕܫ̈ܢܝܢ ܐܠܦ. ܐܫܬܡܫܘ ܒܗ ܘܐܬܩܛܠܘܢ ܚ̈ܝܘܬܐ ܣܓ̈ܝܐܬܐ ܒܬܐܛܪܘܢ ܒܝ̈ܘܡܝ ܦܝܠܝܦܘܣ ܡ̇ܠܟܐ ܘܒܢ̈ܘܗܝ. ܗ̇ܘ ܕܐܚܪܝܬ ܒܬܪ ܫܒܥ ܫ̈ܢܝܢ ܕܡܠܟܘܬܗ ܐܬܩܛܠ ܡܢ ܕܩܝܣ ܗ̇ܘ ܕܥܒܕ  ܪܕܘܦܝܐ ܣܓܝܐܐ ܥܠ ܟܪ̈ܣܛܝܢܐ. ܏ܘܫ<locus from="150a" to="150a"/>
                </incipit>
                <quote xml:lang="syr">
                  <locus from="150b"/>ܗܠܝܢ ܕܝܢ ܐܝܬܝܗܘܢ ܫܡܗ̈ܝܗܘܢ ܕܛ̈ܠܝܐ: ܗܠܝܢ ܕܥܪܩܘ ܗܘܘ: ܐܟܠܝܕܢܣ. ܘܕܝܡܕܣ. ܘܐܘܓܢܝܣ. ܘܐܣܛܦܢܘܣ: ܘܦܪܒܛܝܣ: ܘܣܒܛܝܣ: ܘܩܘܪܝܩܘܣ: ܒ̈ܢܝ ܪ̈ܘܪܒܐ ܕܡܕܝܢܬܐ</quote>
                <note>The names of the youths are given on <locus from="150b">fol. 150 b</locus>.</note>
                <note>Compare <bibl>Add. 12,160<ptr target="https://bl.syriac.uk/ms/35"/>, <citedRange unit="fol" from="147a">fol. 147 a</citedRange>
                  </bibl>, and the <bibl>Acta Sanctt. for July, t. vi., p. 389, Acta alia etc.</bibl>
                </note>
              </msItem>
              <msItem xml:id="b5" n="9">
                <locus from="157a" to="159">157a-159</locus>
                <author>Simeon, bishop of the Persian Christians</author>
                <title type="supplied">The letter of Simeon, bishop of the Persian Christians, to <persName>Simeon</persName>, abbat of <placeName>Gabula</placeName>, regarding the Himyarite martyrs</title>
                <incipit xml:lang="syr">ܐܓܪܬܐ ܕܫܕܪ ܫܡܥܘܢ ܐܦܝܣܩܘܦܐ ܐܘܟܝ ܐܦܩܪܝܣܪܐ $ܕܡܗ̈ܝܡܢܐ ܡܢ ܒܝܬ ܦܪ̈ܣܝܐ: ܠܫܡܥܘܢ ܪܝܫ ܕܝܪܐ ܕܓܒܘܠܐ: ܕܡܘܕܥ ܒܗ̇ ܥܠ ܣ̈ܗܕܐ ܕܐܬܩܛܠܘ ܒܢܓܪܢܡܕܝܢܬ ܡܠܟܘܬܐ ܕܒܝܬ ܚܡܝܪ̈ܝܐ: ܒܫܢܬ ܬܡ̈ܢܡܐܐ ܘܬܠ̈ܬܝܢ ܘܚ̈ܡܫ ܕܝܘ̈ܢܝܐ <foreign xml:lang="en">(A.D. 524)</foreign>: ܫܢܬ ܫ̈ܬ ܕܡܠܟܘܬܗ ܕܝܘܣܛܝܢܣ: ܘܐܦ ܬܫܥܝܬܗܘܢ ܕܣܗ̈ܕܐ ܗ̣ܝ ܐܝܬܝܗ..<locus from="157a" to="157a"/>
                </incipit>
                <note>See <bibl>Assemani, Bibl. Or., t. i., p. 364</bibl>.</note>
              </msItem>
              <msItem xml:id="b6" n="10">
                <locus from="160a" to="165">160a-165</locus>
                
                <title type="supplied">The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1611">Archelides</persName> (Archelaides?)</title>
                <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܕܥܠ ܩܕܝܫܐ ܐܪܟܝܠܝܕܘܣܗ̇ܘ ܕܒܕܘܒܪ̈ܐ ܕܥܢܘܝܘܬܐ ܫܦܪ ܠܐܠܗܐ ܘܐܬܢܨܚ ܒܕܝܪܐ ܕܒܝܪ ܡܪܝ ܡܝܢܐ<!--Margain notes?-->
                  <locus from="160a" to="160a"/>
                </rubric>
                <note>Marg.</note>
                <quote xml:lang="syr">ܐܪܟܝܠܝܕܝܣ<locus from="160a" to="160a"/>
                </quote>
                <note>He was the son of <persName>Gallienus</persName> (ܓܠܝܢܐ) and <persName>Augusta</persName> (ܐܓܘܣܛܐ), citizens of Constantinople in the time of <persName>Gratian</persName> and <persName>Valentinian</persName>.</note>
              </msItem>
              <msItem xml:id="b7" n="11" defective="true">
                <locus from="165b" to="171b">
                  <!-- Enter human-readable locus also -->
                </locus>
                
                <title type="supplied">The history of <persName ref="http://syriaca.org/person/1268">Hilaria</persName>, the daughter of the emperor <persName>Zeno</persName>
                </title>
                <rubric xml:lang="syr">ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܕܥܠ ܩܕܝܫܬܐ ܐܠܐܪܝܐ ܒܪܬܗ ܕܙܝܢܘܢ ܡ̇ܠܟܐ<locus from="165b" to="165b"/>
                </rubric>
                <finalRubric xml:lang="syr">ܫܠ̣ܡܬ̇ ܬܫܥܝܬܐ ܕܥܠ ܩܕܝܫܬܐ ܐ̇ܠܐܪܝܐ. ܒܪܬܗ ܕܙܝܢܘܢ ܡ̇ܠܟܐ. ܕܫܢ̣ܝܬ̇ ܡܢ ܒܝܬ ܐܒܗ̈ܝܗ̇ ܡܛܫܝܐܝܬ݂. ܘܐܬܥܢܘܼܝܬ̇. ܒܡܕܒܪܐ ܗ̇ܝ ܕܒܡܨܪܝܢ<locus from="171b" to="171b"/>
                </finalRubric>
              </msItem>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <p>Vellum, about 11 5/8 in. by 9, consisting of 171 leaves,
            some of which are much stained and torn, especially foll. 1, 9,
            39, 99, 109, 111—114, 116, and 171. The quires, signed with letters,
            were 20 in number, but the first is lost, and <foreign xml:id="syr">ܝܓ</foreign> is imperfect, leaves
            being missing after foll. 110 and 114. Each page is divided into two
            columns, of from 30 to 38 lines in the older portions of the volume,
            and from 20 to 36 in the more recent. 
            </p>
            <objectDesc form="codex">
              <supportDesc material="perg">
                <support>
                  <material>Vellum</material>
                </support>
                <extent>
                  <measure type="composition" unit="leaf" quantity="171">171 ff.</measure>
                  <dimensions type="leaf" unit="in">
                    <height>
                      <measure type="height" quantity="11.625" unit="in">11 5/8</measure>
                    </height>
                    <width>
                      <measure type="width" quantity="9" unit="in">9</measure>
                    </width>
                  </dimensions>
                </extent>
                <foliation type="ancient"/>
                <collation>
                  <p>The quires, signed with letters, were 20 in number, but the first is lost, and ܝܓ is imperfect, leaves being missing after<locus from="110" to="114">foll. 110 and 114</locus>.</p>
                </collation>
                <condition>
                  <list>
                    <item>
                      <p>Vellum, about 11 5/8 in. by 9, consisting of 171 leaves, some of which are much stained and torn, especially<locus from="1" to="171">foll. 1, 9, 39, 99, 109, 111—114, 116, and 171.</locus>
                      </p>
                    </item>
                  </list>
                </condition>
              </supportDesc>
              <layoutDesc>
                <layout columns="2" writtenLines="30 38">
                  <locus from="1a" to="131"/>
                  <p>Each page is divided into two columns, of from 30 to 38 lines in the older portions of the volume.</p>
                </layout>
                <layout columns="2" writtenLines="20 32">
                  <locus from="132a" to="171b"/>
                  <p>Each page is divided into two columns, of from 20 to 36 lines in the more recent portions of the volume.</p>
                </layout>
              </layoutDesc>
            </objectDesc>
            <handDesc hands="2">
              <handNote xml:id="handNote1" scope="major" script="syr-Syre" medium="unknown">
                <desc>The greater part of this manuscript, from the <locus from="1" to="131">beginning to fol. 131</locus>, is written in a fine, regular Estrangela of the <origDate notBefore="0500" notAfter="0600">vith cent.</origDate>
                </desc>
              </handNote>
              <handNote xml:id="handNote2" scope="minor" script="syr" medium="unknown">
                <desc>Foll. <locus from="1" to="8">1—8</locus>, <locus from="19">19</locus>, <locus from="28" to="29">28, 29</locus>, <locus from="38" to="38">38</locus>, <locus from="59" to="59">59</locus>, <locus from="68" to="68">68</locus>, <locus from="89" to="90">89, 90</locus>, <locus from="97" to="98">97, 98</locus>, <locus from="100" to="100">100</locus>, <locus from="107" to="107">107</locus>, <locus from="125" to="126">125, 126</locus>, and <locus from="131" to="131">131</locus> are in a plain, legible hand of the <date notBefore="0900" notAfter="1100">xth or xith cent.</date> The later scribe has added foll. <locus from="132" to="171">132—171</locus>.</desc>
              </handNote>
            </handDesc>
            <decoDesc/>
            <additions>
              <list>
                <item xml:id="addition1" n="1">
                  <locus from="160a" to="160a"/>
                  <p>marg.</p>
                  <p>
                    <quote xml:lang="syr" ref="#handNote2">ܐܪܟܝܠܝܕܝܣ</quote>
                  </p>
                </item>
              </list>
            </additions>
            <bindingDesc/>
            <sealDesc/>
            <accMat/>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <origDate notBefore="0500" notAfter="0600">vith cent.</origDate>
              <origPlace/>
            </origin>
            <provenance/>
            <acquisition/>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <recordHist>
                <source>Manuscript description based on<bibl>
                    <ref target="#Wrightpart">Wright's Catalogue</ref>
                  </bibl>. abbreviated by the Syriaca.org editors.</source>
              </recordHist>
              <note/>
            </adminInfo>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl xml:id="Wrightpart">
                <author>William Wright</author>
                <title xml:lang="en">Catalogue of Syriac Manuscripts in the British Museum Acquired since the Year 1838</title>
                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                <date>1870</date>
                <ptr target="http://syriaca.org/bibl/8"/>
                <citedRange unit="entry">DCCCCXVIII</citedRange>
                <citedRange unit="pp">3:1042-1046</citedRange>
              <ref type="internet-archive-pdf" target="https://archive.org/details/catalogueofsyria03brituoft/page/1042"/>
              </bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </additional>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <interpretation>
          <p>Description is based on Wright's Catalogue without consultation of physical
            manuscripts. Foliation is approximate. Wright often does not indicate ending folia so
            those have been assumed based on beginning folia.</p>
          <p>Scribal notes which could not be more clearly classified based on Wright's descriptions
            have been identified as &lt;addition&gt;s whether they occur in the margins or the body
            of the manuscript.</p>
          <p>In general, we have classified as an &lt;msItem&gt; as much of the manuscript contents
            as possible, including tables of contents and indices.</p>
        </interpretation>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="Wright-BL-Taxonomy">
          <bibl>
            
            <ptr target="http://syriaca.org/documentation/Wright-BL-Taxonomy.html"/>
          </bibl>
          <category xml:id="biblical-manuscripts">
            <category xml:id="bible-ot">
              <catDesc>Old Testament</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="bible-nt">
              <catDesc>New Testament</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="bible-apocrypha">
              <catDesc>Apocrypha</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="bible-punctuation">
              <catDesc>Punctuation</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="service-books">
            <category xml:id="psalter">
              <catDesc>Psalters</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="lectionaries">
              <catDesc>Lectionaries</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="missals">
              <catDesc>Missals</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="sacerdotals">
              <catDesc>Sacerdotals</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="choral">
              <catDesc>Choral Books</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="hymns">
              <catDesc>Hymns</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="prayers">
              <catDesc>Prayers</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="funerals">
              <catDesc>Funeral Services</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="theology">
            <category xml:id="theo-single">
              <catDesc>Individual Authors</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="theo-collected">
              <catDesc>Collected Authors</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="theo-catenae">
              <catDesc>Catenae Patrum and Demonstrations against Heresies</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="theo-anonymous">
              <catDesc>Anonymous Works</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="theo-council">
              <catDesc>Councils of the Church and Ecclesiastical Canons</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="wright-history">
            <category xml:id="history">
              <catDesc>History</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="lives">
            <category xml:id="lives-collect">
              <catDesc>Collected Lives</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="lives-single">
              <catDesc>Single Lives</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="scientific-lit">
            <category xml:id="sci-logic">
              <catDesc>Logic and Rhetoric</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="sci-grammar">
              <catDesc>Grammar and Lexicography</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="sci-ethics">
              <catDesc>Ethics</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="sci-medicine">
              <catDesc>Medicine</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="sci-agriculture">
              <catDesc>Agriculture</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="sci-chemistry">
              <catDesc>Chemistry</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="sci-natural-history">
              <catDesc>Natural History</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="wright-fly-leaves">
            <category xml:id="fly-leaves">
              <catDesc>Fly Leaves</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="appendices">
            <category xml:id="appendix-a">
              <catDesc>Appendix A</catDesc>
            </category>
            <category xml:id="appendix-b">
              <catDesc>Appendix B</catDesc>
            </category>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="unclassified">
            <catDesc>Unclassified</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="syr">Unvocalized Syriac of any variety or period</language>
        <language ident="syr-Syre">Syriac in Estrangela</language>
        <language ident="syr-Syrj">Vocalized West Syriac</language>
        <language ident="syr-Syrn">Vocalized East Syriac</language>
        <language ident="syr-x-syrm">Melkite Syriac</language>
        <language ident="syr-x-syrp">Palestinian Syriac</language>
        <language ident="ar-Syrc">Unvocalized or Undetermined Arabic Garshuni</language>
        <language ident="ar-Syrj">Arabic Garshuni in Vocalized West Syriac Script</language>
        <language ident="ar-Syrn">Arabic Garshuni in Vocalized East Syriac Script</language>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
        <language ident="ar">Arabic</language>
        <language ident="fr">French</language>
        <language ident="de">German</language>
        <language ident="la">Latin</language>
        <language ident="grc">Ancient Greek</language>
        <language ident="cop">Coptic</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#Wright-BL-Taxonomy">
          <list>
            <item>
              <ref target="#history"/>
            </item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <change who="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#kurban" when="2023-04-21-05:00">CHANGED: added or corrected folio extent values</change>
      <change who="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#jarnwine" when="2023-01-13-06:00">ADDED: supplied and corrected Syriaca.org URIs for authors</change>
      <change who="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#jarnwine" when="2022-05-05">Updates to physDesc</change>
      <change who="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#pgmiller" when="2015-10-19">Created: file</change>
      <change type="planned" subtype="reconstruction">One or more msParts need to be encoded into an historical reconstruction of a no longer extant manuscript..</change>
      <change who="https://bl.syriac.uk/documentation/editors.xml#pgmiller" when="2016-07-06">Changed: Files moved to srophe-app-data/data/manuscripts/tei repository.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <facsimile>
    <!-- facsimile information about the manuscript -->
    <graphic/>
    <!-- Alternatively you could provide 'surface' elements with more than one image per surface, and optionally with 'zone' 
      elements to give coordinates for any special areas of interest -->
  </facsimile>
  <text>
    <body>
      <!-- If you had a transcription of the manuscript you would put it here -->
      <p/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>